Finding Aid for United Church of Christ. Michigan Conference records, 1840-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
United Church of Christ. Michigan Conference records
1840-2013
United Church of Christ. Michigan Conference.
86256 Ba 2 UAl
The Michigan Conference of the United Church of Christ was formed from the merger of the Michigan Conference of the Congregational Church and the Michigan-Indiana Synod of the Evangelical and Reformed Church. The record group includes retired records of individual associations, conferences, and local churches. Also included are files on churches and pastors within the Conference.
26 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records are on deposit from the Michigan Conference (donor no. 4591). The records of the Ann Arbor Regional Women's Guild came from Mrs. Elvira Vogel (donor no. 7908 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The United Church of Christ was formed from the merger in 1957 of the Congregational Christian Church and the Evangelical and Reformed Church. Subsequently, on April 17, 1963, the Michigan Congregational Conference and the Michigan-Indiana Synod of the Evangelical and Reformed Church merged to form the Michigan Conference of the United Church of Christ.
The Congregational churches of Michigan were organized into a State Association on October 11, 1842. Previously, in May 1840, the Eastern Association and Conference had been organized for the southeastern portion of the state; in 1841, the Marshall Conference (later Olivet Conference) was established, followed by the Jackson Conference in May 1842. Church leaders at the time believed that if the church was ever to become strong and efficient in the state it would need a state-wide association. The formal name of the new organization was the General Association of the Congregational Ministers and Churches of Michigan.
As of 2014, the United Church of Christ Michigan Conference consisted of the following six associations: Covenant, Detroit Metropolitan, Eastern, GrandWest, Southwest, and United Northern. The collection contains records from each of these associations.
Each of these individual associations are the product of mergers between smaller associations of churches. The Covenant Association consists of mergers between several associations. The Jackson Association (organized in 1842) merged with the Ann Arbor Region, Evangelical and Reformed Churches in 1964 to become the Ann Arbor-Jackson Association. In 1978, the Ann Arbor-Jackson Association merged with the Central Association (organized in 1845) to become the Covenant Association.
In 1993, the Grand Rapids Association and the West Michigan Association merged to form the GrandWest Association.
This record group is comprised primarily of records of the associations and conferences that make up the United Church of Christ Michigan Conference. The records document the mergers between smaller conferences to make the larger ones of today. These records are largely made up of correspondence, minutes, agendas, conference materials, and programming information.
Besides records of the individual associations and conferences, the collection also contains an extensive amount of records from individual churches, which can be found in the "Records from individual churches" and the "Church files" series. Because their relationship to each other is unknown, these series were not combined. The "Church files" series are records that may have been stored by the Michigan Conference rather than the individual churches. The "Records from individual churches" concerns materials that belonged to the individual churches. Whether these churches belonged to the smaller associations that make up the Michigan Conference is unknown. Therefore, they were kept separate. More information on these series can be found in the individual series' description below.
The record group has been arranged into the following series: Michigan Conference; Associations and conferences; Woman's Home Missionary Union and related; Records from individual churches; Annual Meetings of Michigan Congregational Conference and of the United Church of Christ; Evangelical and Reformed Church; Church files; Photographs; Ministerial files; and Student ministry.
Subjects:
Cheboygan Association of Congregational Churches (Mich.); Eastern Association of the Congregational Churches and Ministers of Michigan.; Genesee Association of Congregational Churches and Ministers (Mich.); Gladstone Association of Congregational Churches (Mich.); Grand Traverse Association of Congregational Churches (Mich.); Lansing Association of Congregational Churches and Ministers (Mich.); Michigan Congregational Christian Conference.; Olivet Association of Congregational Churches and Ministers (Mich.); Saginaw Association of Congregational Churches and Ministers (Mich.); Congregational churches--Michigan.Michigan.; Congregational churches--Michigan--Eastmanville.MichiganEastmanville.; Congregational churches--Michigan--Hopkins.MichiganHopkins.; Congregational churches--Michigan--South Boston.MichiganSouth Boston.; Congregational churches--Michigan--Stanton.MichiganStanton.; Congregational churches--Michigan--Victor.MichiganVictor.; Congregational churches--Michigan--West Branch.MichiganWest Branch.; Congregational Church (Stanton, Mich.); Eastmanville (Mich.); Evangelical and Reformed Church. Michigan-Indiana Synod.; First Congregational Church (Eastmanville, Mich.); First Congregational Church (South Boston, Mich.); First Congregational Church (Victor, Michigan); First Congregational Church (West Branch, Mich.); First Congregational Society (Hopkins, Mich.); Hopkins (Mich.); South Boston (Mich.); Stanton (Mich.); United Church of Christ. Michigan Conference.; Victor (Mich.); West Branch (Mich.); United Church of Christ. Covenant Association (Mich.); United Church of Christ. Detroit Metropolitan Association (Mich.); United Church of Christ. GrandWest Association (Mich.); United Church of Christ. United Northern Association (Mich.); Nativity United Church of Christ (Livonia, Mich.); St. Paul United Church of Christ (Lansing, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Baker Memorial Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Brimley (Mich.); Carriages and coaches.; Carts and wagons.; Churches--Michigan--Drummond Island.; Churches--Michigan--Ewen.; Churches--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Churches--Michigan--Jackson.; Churches--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Clergy.; Congregational Church Parsonage (Iroquois, Mich.); Congregational Church Parsonage (Vienna, Mich.); Drummond Island (Mich.)--Churches.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ensign.; Dwellings--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Dwellings--Michigan--Iroquois.; Dwellings--Michigan--Vienna.; Ensign (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ewen (Mich.); Ewen (Mich.)--Churches.; First Congregational Church (Jackson, Mich.); First Congregational Church (Kalamazoo, Mich.); Frontier and pioneer life--Michigan.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Churches.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Streets.; Interiors.; Iroquois (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Jackson (Mich.)--Churches.; Kalamazoo (Mich.)--Churches.; Log cabins.; Park Congregational Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Streets--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Sugar Island (Mich.); Trout Creek (Mich.); Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Vienna (Mich.)--Dwellings.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Poster board.; VHS.
- Michigan Conference
  The Michigan Conference series (2 linear feet) contains records of the Michigan Conference. There is a record book dating from 1855 that contains the constitution and proceedings of the annual session. There are also minutes of the Executive Committee and Board of Trustees of the Michigan Congregational Conference between 1890 and 1963. This series also contains minutes from of the Property Management and Development committee. It contains newsletters and newspapers that were published by the Michigan Conference. There are also publications from other churches, which includes a cookbook and a history of the First Congregational Church of Battle Creek. Finally, there is a VHS tape by St. Paul United Church of Christ that records their closing service on April 19, 1998.
  - Michigan Association of Christian Churches (Box 1)
    - Record Book, 1855-1892 (Box 1)
      (include constitution and proceedings of annual session)
  - Executive Committee and Board of Trustees of the Michigan Congregational Conference
    - Minutes, 1890-1908 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1908-1920 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1920-1927 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1928-1949 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1949-1963 (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees of the General Association of Congregational Churches and Ministers, Committee on Home Missions
    - Minutes, 1886-1908 (Box 1)
  - Minutes (Box 25)
    - Property Management and Development, 1966-1976 (Box 25)
  - Newsletters
    - Conference Connections, 1998-2001 (Box 25)
    - Michigan Conference News, 2002 (Box 25)
  - Newspapers
    - In the Michigan Conference, 2002-2009 (Box 25)
  - Publications
    - Cooking with Love and Memories, Six Lakes United Church of Christ (Box 25)
    - First Congregational Church of Battle Creek: Its First One-Hundred and Fifty years, 1836-1986 (Box 25)
    - Make Ahead Favorites: Foods with a Flair, Huron Shores Business and Professional Women's Club (Box 25)
  - VHS tape, St. Paul United Church of Christ, Closing Service: Remembrance and Appreciation, 1998 (Box 25)
- Associations and conferences
  The Associations and conferences series (8 linear feet) contains the records of the associations and conferences that make up the Michigan Conference. Some of these associations and conferences do not currently exist. Other associations, such as the Covenant Association, are made up of several associations that merged. In this case, the individual associations make up a group within that association. The journals within the series contains meeting minutes, reports, and information about the association. Record books contain similar information. Meeting records contain meeting minutes and agendas. The records were kept in the original order of the creator. Therefore, in some instances council and association minutes are contained within the same folder (indicated by "council/association minutes"). The series also contains a scrapbook of the Boulevard Congregational Church (Box 20), which contains pictures, bulletins, and newsletters of the church. Committee papers include correspondence, meeting minutes, and meeting agendas. In addition, the series contains annual reports and newsletters.
  - Gladstone Association
    - Journal, 1888-1918 (Box 2)
  - Olivet Association
    - Journal, 1875-1909 (Box 2)
  - Cheboygan Congregational Conference
    - Journal, 1894-1925 (Box 2)
  - Genesee Association / Conference
    - Constitution of Genesee and Grand River Conference 1846 also Journal of Genesee Conference, 1846-1856 (Box 2)
    - Journal, 1857-1877 (Box 2)
    - Journal, 1877-1920 (Box 2)
    - Constitution and membership (Box 2)
    - Cash book, 1878-1934 (Box 2)
    - Historical sketch (Box 2)
  - Grand Traverse Congregational Conference (Box 3)
    - Journal, 1878-1926 (Box 3)
  - Saginaw Conference
    - Journal, 1885-1928 (Box 3)
  - Lansing Association
    - Records, 1880-1934 (Box 3)
  - Eastern Conference
    - Record book, 1840-1881 (Box 3)
    - Record book, 1881-1907 (Box 3)
  - Covenant Association (Box 19)
    - Ann Arbor-Jackson Association
      - Annual reports, 1967-1975; 2 folders (Box 19)
      - Bylaws, 1964 (Box 19)
      - Council/Association minutes, 1965-1972; 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Executive committee minutes/records, 1965-1978 (Box 19)
      - Merger documents, 1962-1964; 4 folders (Box 19)
    - Annual meetings, 1978-1992; 14 folders (Box 19)
    - Central Association
      - Bylaws and founding documents (Box 19)
      - Correspondence, 1964-1977 (Box 19)
      - Manual of the Congregational Christian Churches, 1947 (Box 19)
      - Meeting minutes and programs, 1960s-1970s; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Records, 1958-1967; 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Reports, 1965-1977 (Box 20)
    - Council records, 1978-1992; 8 folders (Box 20)
    - Formation records
      - Correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 20)
      - Meeting records, 1963-1978 (Box 20)
    - Jackson Association
      - Constitution (Box 20)
      - Minutes
        - Advisory committee, 1957-1962 (Box 20)
        - Association, 1957-1964 (Box 20)
  - Detroit Metropolitan Association
    - Association/Board of Trustees minutes, 1963-1970; 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Scrapbook of Boulevard Congregational Church, 1945-1970 (Box 20)
    - Women's Fellowship Records, 1964-1971; 6 folders (Box 21)
  - GrandWest Association
    - Grand Rapids Area Association
      - Annual reports, 1972-1993; 19 folders (Box 21)
      - Articles of incorporation and bylaws, 1979-1992 (Box 21)
      - Black Church Start-Grand Rapids, 1980s (Box 21)
      - Budget notes, 1982-1990 (Box 21)
      - Committee on Church Development, 1982-1987 (Box 21)
      - Committee on Church and Ministry Policy and Guidelines Manual, 1986 (Box 21)
      - Committee on Church and Society, 1982-1988 (Box 21)
      - Committee on Congregational Life, 1982-1990 (Box 21)
      - Correspondence, 1982-1990 (Box 22)
      - Council, 1968-1989 (Box 22)
      - Council for Planning and Correlation, 1980s (Box 22)
      - Division of Mission and Social Action, 1983-1984 (Box 22)
      - Leadership Exchange Day, 1980s (Box 22)
      - Manuals and studies (Box 22)
      - Mission statement, 1983 (Box 22)
      - New Church Start, 1979-1980 (Box 22)
      - New Initiatives Task Force, 1982 (Box 22)
      - Newsletters, 1982-1989 (Box 22)
      - Outreach-Riverside Project, 1980-1983 (Box 22)
      - Specialized Ministries-Smith Outreach Ministry and United Church Outreach Ministries, 1981-1984 (Box 22)
      - Staff-Associate Conference Minister, reports, correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 22)
      - United Church Outreach Ministry
        - Bylaws, 1985-1988 (Box 22)
        - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 22)
        - Minutes/reports, 1985-1989 (Box 22)
        - UCOM News, 1988-1990 (Box 22)
      - UCC Women-1985 annual report and flyers, 1980s (Box 22)
      - West Area Associate Conference minister's files, Reverend Larry Stanton, 1979-1982; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Women and Men's Task Force (Box 22)
      - World Missioner Task Force
        - Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 22)
        - Evaluation, 1982-1985 (Box 22)
        - Minutes, 1980-1982 (Box 22)
        - Reports, 1980-1982 (Box 22)
    - West Michigan Association
      - Board minutes, 1965-1971 (Box 22)
      - Committee documents
        - Christian Nurture (Box 22)
        - Church in Society (Box 22)
        - Stewardship, Education, and Finance (Box 22)
      - Constitution and bylaws (Box 22)
      - Correspondence, 1980s (Box 22)
      - Merger documents, 1993-1994 (Box 22)
      - Minutes, 1980s (Box 22)
      - Newsletters, 1980s (Box 22)
      - Reports, 1980s (Box 22)
  - Southwest Association
    - Annual meetings (6 of 22 folders), 1964-1992 (Box 22)
    - Annual meetings (16 of 22 folders), 1964-1992 (Box 23)
    - Articles of Association and bylaws, 1983 (Box 23)
    - Committee records
      - Christian Nurture, 1978-1990 (Box 23)
      - Church Development, 1984-1990 (Box 23)
      - Church in Mission, 1981-1982 (Box 23)
      - Church in Society, 1984-1990 (Box 23)
      - Congregational Life, 1983-1988 (Box 23)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 23)
    - Council records (3 of 11 folders), 1964-1991 (Box 23)
    - Council records (8 of 11 folders), 1964-1991 (Box 24)
    - Executive Committee records, 1964-1965; 1980-1985; 5 folders (Box 24)
    - Financial
      - Budgets, 1969-1977 (Box 24)
      - Year end statements, 1984-1989 (Box 24)
    - Histories, 1991; 2009 (Box 24)
    - Membership statistics, 1975-1984 (Box 24)
    - Minister's records, 1919-2007 (Box 24)
    - Missionaries in Residence, Howard and Anna May Towne, 1987 (Box 24)
    - New Initiatives in Church Development, 1982-1983 (Box 24)
    - Newsletters, 1981-1992; 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Retreats
      - Clergy/spouse, 1979-1981 (Box 24)
      - Council and Committees, 1991 (Box 24)
  - United Northern Association
    - Cheboygan Association, Minutes and correspondence, 1970s (Box 24)
    - Grand Traverse Association, Minutes and correspondence, 1970s (Box 24)
    - Meeting minutes, 1981 (Box 24)
- Woman's Home Missionary Union and related
  The Woman's Home Missionary Union and related series (1 linear foot) contains records of the Woman's Home Missionary Union and related women's organizations. Record books contain information such as minutes and committee information. The series also includes financial ledgers.
  - Record book include constitution and reports from local missionary societies, 1873-1890 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees record book, 1891-1926 (Box 4)
  - Executive Board record book, 1909-1918 (Box 4)
  - Executive Board record book, 1918-1926 (Box 4)
  - Record book of annual meetings, 1892-1908 (Box 4)
  - Record book of annual meetings, 1909-1935 (Box 4)
  - Minutes of the Women's Department of the Executive Board, 1936-1943 (Box 4)
  - Minutes of the First Congregational Ladies Sewing Society of Jackson, 1847-1880 (Box 4)
  - Woman's Foreign Missionary Society, Kalamazoo Association
    - Minutes, 1881-1909 (Box 4)
    - Minutes, 1910-1938 (Box 4)
  - Financial ledger of the Women's Fellowship, Kalamazoo Association, 1947-1957 (Box 4)
  - Woman's Missionary Society of the Congregational Church of Hancock, Michigan
    - Treasurer's book, 1884-1904 (Box 4)
    - Record book, 1884-1890 (Box 4)
    - Record book, 1902-1906 (Box 4)
- Records from individual churches
  The Records from individual churches series (3 linear feet and 1 outsize folder) contains items from individual churches that were donated separately from their associated conference. In Box 4, there is a scrapbook from the First Congregational Church of Stanton. There are also journals and record books from individual churches that contain meeting minutes, agendas, and by-laws. In addition, there is about one linear foot of records from the Nativity United Church of Christ in Livonia, Michigan. A significant portion of their records consists of church bulletins from their services between the years 2000 and 2011. There are two histories of the church included within the collection that were written in 1986 and 2013. Finally, there are display folders contained within an outsize folder that displays photographs and information of the congregation's history.
  The series also contains minutes of the Grand Rapids Association of Congregational Ministers and Wives from 1910-1957. In addition, the series contains the Schmid letters, which were written by a pioneer German missionary. There are also histories of Michigan Congregational Churches. The biographical sketches are brief essays on various early ministers in Michigan. The miscellaneous folder contains volume one of The History of Congregational Churches in Maine by Calvin Clark. It also includes a prayer, reports, and pamphlets.
  - Scrapbook of the First Congregational Church of Stanton, 1902-1914 (Box 4)
  - Journal of the Victor Congregational Church (Clinton County), 1855-1870 (Box 5)
  - Record of the First Congregational Church of Victor, 1887-1906 (Box 5)
  - Journal of the First Congregational Church, Sault St. Marie Conference, 1887-1907 (Box 5)
  - Journal of the Eastlake Church, 1900-1913 (Box 5)
  - Journal of the Hopkins Ladies Aid Society, 1909-1928 (Box 5)
  - Record book of The First Congregational Church of West Branch, 1888-1906 (Box 5)
  - Record of the Maple Congregational Church of Shiawassee, 1840-1843 (Box 5)
  - Record of the First Congregational Church of South Boston, Mich., 1877-1930 (Box 5)
  - Record books of the First Congregational Society of Hopkins, 1858-1938; 3 volumes (Box 5)
  - Record books of the First Congregational Church of Eastmanville (Ottawa County), circa 1864-1910; 3 volumes (Box 5)
  - Nativity United Church of Christ (Livonia) (Box 26)
    - Annual Reports, 1956-1972; 2005-2012; 4 folders (Box 26)
    - Audit Report, 2007 (Box 26)
    - Church Bulletins, 2000-2011; 13 folders (Box 26)
    - Communion Service Liturgies (Box 26)
    - Constitution and bylaws, 1993 (Box 26)
    - History, 1986; 2013 (Box 26)
    - Minutes, December 19, 1993 (Box 26)
    - Display boards of congregation history (Folder 1)
  - Congregational Club of Eastern Michigan Minutes, 1889-1902 (Box 6)
  - Minutes of Board of Trustees of the Michigan Home Missionary Society, 1907-1908 (Box 6)
  - Records of the Michigan Congregational Ministerial Relief Society, 1883-1897 (Box 6)
  - Records concerning minister receiving parsonage boxes, 1933-1934 (Box 6)
  - American Congregational Union-Records of recommendations made for grants to churches from, June 1, 1883-1909 (Box 6)
  - Records of the Board of Directors of Home Missions, 1879-1889 (Box 6)
  - Financial records, 1933-1938 (Box 6)
  - Papers concerning the Evangelical Home for Children and Aged (Box 6)
  - The Running Record [newsletter of the Michigan Conference of the United Church of Christ], 1967-1969 (Box 6)
  - Grand Rapids Association of Congregational Ministers and Wives
    - Minutes, 1910-1917 (Box 7)
    - Minutes, 1933-1937 (Box 7)
    - Minutes, 1938-1941 (Box 7)
    - Minutes, 1942-1944 (Box 7)
    - Minutes, 1945-1947 (Box 7)
    - Minutes, 1948-1952 (Box 7)
    - Minutes, 1953-1954 (Box 7)
    - Minutes, 1955-1957 (Box 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 7)
  - The Schmid Letters (pioneer German Missionary) (Box 7)
  - History of Michigan Congregationalism, circa 1931 (Box 7)
  - Histories of Michigan Congregational Churches (Box 7)
  - Biographical sketches (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook: Twelfth biennial meeting of the General Council of the Congregational Christian Churches, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Conference miscellanea, including volume one of The History of Congregational Churches in Maine by Calvin Clark (Box 7)
- Annual Meetings of Michigan Congregational Conference, beginning in annual meetings of the United Church of Christ, 1964
  The Annual Meetings of the Michigan Congregational Conference and of the United Church of Christ series (0.5 linear feet) contains meeting records, including minutes and agendas, of the annual meetings of the Michigan Congregational Conference from 1910-1963. It also contains meeting minutes and agendas from the annual meetings of the United Church of Christ (which formed from the Michigan Congregational Conference) between 1964-1967 and 1976.
  - Various annual meetings, 1910-1961 (Box 5)
  - 120th annual meeting, 1962 (Box 6)
  - 121st annual meeting, 1963 (Box 6)
  - 1st annual meeting of the United Church of Christ, 1964 (Box 6)
  - 2nd annual meeting of the United Church of Christ, 1965 (Box 6)
  - 3rd annual meeting of the United Church of Christ, 1966 (Box 6)
  - 4th annual meeting of the United Church of Christ, 1967 (Box 6)
  - 13th annual meeting of the United Church of Christ, 1976 (Box 6)
- Evangelical and Reformed Church (Box 7)